Guide to the Peter E. Palmquist Collection of Photography and Photographic Formats
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Photographs by Format, circa 1855-1940; Series IV; 16.6; (57 boxes)
  - Tintypes and Wet Collodion Processes
    - Studio Portrait Tintypes
      - Studio Portraits of Boys
        - Boy posed sitting, half figure (Box 68, Folder 753)
        - Boy posed sitting, bust figure (Box 68, Folder 754)
        - Boy posed standing, full-length figure (Box 68, Folder 755)
        - Boy posed reclining, full-length figure (Box 68, Folder 756)
      - Studio Portraits of Children
        - Two girls posed standing or sitting (Box 69, Folder 757)
        - Girl posed standing and a girl posed sitting (Box 69, Folder 758)
        - Girl posed standing and a boy posed sitting (Box 69, Folder 759)
        - Girl posed sitting and a boy posed standing (Box 69, Folder 760)
        - Boy posed standing and a boy posed sitting (Box 69, Folder 761)
        - Two boys posed standing (Box 69, Folder 762)
        - Two boys posed sitting (Box 69, Folder 763)
        - Two girls and a boy (Box 69, Folder 764)
        - Three girls (Box 69, Folder 765)
      - Studio Portraits of Children and Adults
        - Woman posed with a child (Box 69, Folder 766)
        - Man posed with a child (Box 69, Folder 767)
        - Woman posed with children (Box 69, Folder 768)
        - Man posed with children (Box 69, Folder 769)
        - Woman and man posed with children (Box 69, Folder 770)
        - Multiple adults posed with children (Box 69, Folder 771)
      - Studio Portraits of Women
        - Woman posed sitting, full-length figure (Box 70, Folder 772)
        - Woman posed sitting, half figure (Box 70, Folder 773-774)
        - Woman posed sitting, bust figure (Box 70, Folder 775-776)
        - Woman posed standing, full-length figure (Box 70, Folder 777-778)
        - Woman posed standing, half figure (Box 70, Folder 779)
        - Two women posed sitting (Box 70, Folder 780)
        - Two women posed standing (Box 70, Folder 781)
        - Woman posed sitting and a woman posed standing (Box 70, Folder 782)
      - Studio Portraits of Men
        - Man posed sitting, full-length figure (Box 71, Folder 783)
        - Man posed sitting, half figure (Box 71, Folder 784-785)
        - Man posed sitting, bust figure (Box 71, Folder 786-788)
        - Man posed standing, full-length figure (Box 71, Folder 789-790)
        - Man posed standing, half figure (Box 71, Folder 791)
        - Two men posed sitting (Box 71, Folder 792)
        - Two women posed standing (Box 71, Folder 793)
        - Man posed sitting and a man posed standing (Box 71, Folder 794)
      - Studio Portraits of Men and Women
        - Woman and man posed sitting (Box 72, Folder 795)
        - Woman and man posed standing (Box 72, Folder 796)
        - Woman posed standing and a man posed sitting (Box 72, Folder 797)
        - Woman posed sitting and a man posed standing (Box 72, Folder 798)
        - Three women (Box 72, Folder 799)
        - Three men (Box 72, Folder 800)
        - Two women and a man (Box 72, Folder 801)
        - Two women and two men (Box 72, Folder 802)
        - Four women (Box 72, Folder 803)
        - Four men (Box 72, Folder 804)
        - Five people (Box 72, Folder 805)
        - Six people (Box 72, Folder 806)
        - Seven people (Box 72, Folder 807)
        - Eight people (Box 72, Folder 808)
        - Nine people (Box 72, Folder 809)
        - Ten or more People (Box 72, Folder 810)
      - Studio Portraits of Postmortems
        This component includes examples of postmortem studio portraits, which depict the corpses of deceased individuals.
        - Postmortem portrait of an infant (Box 72, Folder 811)
        - Postmortem portrait of a man (Box 72, Folder 812)
    - Tintypes of Exteriors
      This component consists of tintypes of exterior portraits and views with dimensions less than 8.5 by 6.5 inches.
      - Horses and people (Box 73, Folder 813)
      - Woman posed alone (Box 73, Folder 814)
      - Man posed alone (Box 73, Folder 815)
      - Two women (Box 73, Folder 816)
      - Two men (Box 73, Folder 817)
      - Woman and a man (Box 73, Folder 818)
      - Two boys (Box 73, Folder 819)
      - Three people (Box 73, Folder 820)
      - Five people (Box 73, Folder 821)
      - Eight people (Box 73, Folder 822)
      - Ten or More People (Box 73, Folder 823)
      - View of a house (Box 73, Folder 824)
    - Tintype Copy Photographs
      This component consists of tintypes of copy photographs of studio portraits and an exterior view with dimensions less than 8.5 by 6.5 inches.
      - Boy posed alone (Box 73, Folder 825)
      - Woman posed alone (Box 73, Folder 826)
      - Man posed alone (Box 73, Folder 827)
      - Two women (Box 73, Folder 828)
      - Woman posed with children (Box 73, Folder 829)
      - View of Hayfork, California, circa 1870 (Box 73, Folder 830)
    - Gem Photographs
      This component consists of very small tintypes known as gem photographs, which were popular circa 1865-circa 1880. Gem photographs were usually studio portraits that depict only the face of the subject, and were often mounted in jewelry
      - Dog posed alone (Box 74, Folder 831)
      - Girl posed alone (Box 74, Folder 832)
      - Boy posed alone (Box 74, Folder 833)
      - Woman posed alone (Box 74, Folder 834)
      - Man posed alone (Box 74, Folder 835)
      - Calling cards with gem photographs (Box 74, Folder 836)
        Identified individuals include a boy named Willie Andrews; men including J. G. Darling, Evans Davis, Eugene C. Gage, Ben Hudspeth, and E. R. Libby; and women including Fannie S. Marble and Addie S. Merrills, as well as two different women name Nancy M. Rand
      - Gem Photograph Albums
        - Wing & Chandler, San Jose, California, Wing & Chandler's Gem Album, 1877-1880 (Box 75, Folder 837)
          Owned by Annie "Duckie" Rolena Fouzen, a student at the California State Normal School at San Jose, California
        - Lovewell, Los Angeles, California, Lovewell's Gem Album (Box 75, Folder 838)
          Owned by Mrs. E. A. McPheeter, Marysville, California
        - Gem photograph albums (Box 75, Folder 839-841)
  - Stereograph Cards
    Organized under three headings: Stereograph Card Sets, Stereograph Cards Not in Sets, and Stereoscope.
    Stereograph Cards are double photographs of the same image taken from two slightly different perspectives and mounted on cards, which create a three dimensional effect when viewed through a stereoscope.
    This subseries includes sets of stereograph cards produced by manufacturers and most housed in their original boxes, as well as examples of single stereograph cards and a stereoscope for viewing the cards.
    - Stereograph Card Sets
      - Fred Harvey - TruTone
        - Fifty-Six Scenes of the Grand Canyon of Arizona, circa 1934 (Box 76, Folder 842)
      - Keystone View Company
        - Children of Many Lands (Box 76, Folder 843)
          25 stereograph cards
          Includes 5 stereographs of Underwood & Underwood
        - Norway (Box 76, Folder 844)
          26 stereograph cards
        - Primitive Indians (Box 77, Folder 845)
          31 stereograph cards
          Includes 8 stereograph cards published by Underwood & Underwood
      - Underwood & Underwood
        - Birds and Their Nests, circa 1900 (Box 77, Folder 846)
          32 stereograph cards
        - Grand Canyon Arizona, circa 1903-1909 (Box 77, Folder 847)
          14 stereograph cards
        - Miscellaneous, Volume I (Box 77, Folder 848)
          17 stereograph cards
        - Miscellaneous, Volume II (Box 78, Folder 849)
          15 stereograph cards
        - Niagara Falls, circa 1895-1903 (Box 78, Folder 850)
        - Panama, circa 1900-1907 (Box 78, Folder 851)
          35 stereograph cards
        - Paper Making (Box 78, Folder 852)
        - Rice Industry, circa 1902 (Box 79, Folder 853)
          Includes one stereograph card published by the Keystone View Company
        - Ship Life (Box 79, Folder 854)
          All stereograph cards published by the Keystone View Company in an Underwood & Underwood box
        - Silk Labels (Box 79, Folder 855)
          27 stereograph cards
        - Sugar Industry (Box 79, Folder 856)
          62 stereograph cards
        - United States, Volume I, circa 1900-1910 (Box 80, Folder 857)
          23 stereograph cards
        - United States, Volume II, circa 1900-1910 (Box 80, Folder 858)
        - United States, Volume III, circa 1900-1910 (Box 80, Folder 859)
          28 stereograph cards
        - Washington, circa 1897-1908 (Box 80, Folder 860)
          20 stereograph cards
        - Wild Animals, circa 1895-1908 (Box 81, Folder 861)
          43 stereograph cards
          Includes 1 Keystone card
        - Yellowstone National Park, circa 1904 (Box 81, Folder 862)
          29 stereograph cards
        - Yosemite, circa 1901-1908 (Box 81, Folder 863)
          21 stereograph cards
      - Unidentified photographer, Stereograph cards depicting John Bass, an American bullfighter, circa 1900; 11 stereograph cards (Box 81, Folder 864)
    - Stereograph Cards Not in Sets
      - Anthony, Edward, New York City (Box 82, Folder 865)
      - Averill, Henry Ketchum, Jr., Plattsburgh, New York (Box 82, Folder 866)
      - B. K. Photographie, Paris, France (Box 82, Folder 867)
        Tissue stereograph
      - B. W. Kilburn Company (Box 82, Folder 868)
      - Bennett, Henry Hamilton, Kilbourn, Wisconsin (Box 82, Folder 869)
      - C. H. G., Paris, France (Box 82, Folder 870)
      - Cremer, James, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania (Box 82, Folder 871)
      - E. & H. T. Anthony & Company, New York City (Box 82, Folder 872-873)
      - Frith, Francis, England (Box 82, Folder 874)
      - Graves, Jesse A., Delaware Water Gap, Pennsylvania (Box 82, Folder 875)
      - International Stereoscope Association, Japan (Box 82, Folder 876)
      - Jarvis, John F., Washington, D.C. (Box 82, Folder 877)
      - Keystone View Company (Box 82, Folder 878-882)
      - Montgomery Ward Company, Thornward Series (Box 82, Folder 883)
      - National Stereoscopic Association, Mansfield, Massachusetts, 1975 May 24 (Box 82, Folder 884)
        Photograph by Nicholas M. Graver
      - Photographie C à Paris, France (Box 82, Folder 885)
      - Quaker Oats Company (Box 82, Folder 886)
      - Rau, William Herman, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania (Box 82, Folder 887)
      - Underwood & Underwood (Box 82, Folder 888-890)
      - Stoddard, Seneca Ray, Glens Falls, New York (Box 82, Folder 891)
      - Wendt, Julius M., Albany, New York (Box 82, Folder 892)
      - Walker, Philip Lyon (Box 82, Folder 893)
      - Unidentified photographers (Box 82, Folder 894-906)
    - Stereoscope
      - Underwood & Underwood, Stereoscope, circa 1905 (Box 83)
  - Photographic Prints with Hand Coloring
    Examples of photographic prints with color applied to them by a manual process.
    - Eden Studios, J. M. Penkin with Philip and Gena (Box 84, Folder 907)
    - Harpham, Portrait of a woman (Box 84, Folder 908)
    - Hodges, Family portrait (Box 84, Folder 909)
    - National Copying Co., Portrait of a woman (Box 84, Folder 910)
    - National Copying Co., Portrait of a woman with flowers in her hair (Box 84, Folder 911)
    - R. & K. L., Portrait of a girl holding flowers (Box 84, Folder 912)
    - Sargood & Co., Stella M. Townsend, 1858 January (Box 84, Folder 913)
    - W. E. Hook Co., Glenwood Springs, Colorado, "The Swimming Pool" (Box 84, Folder 914)
    - Whitehurst Gallery, Portrait of a woman (Box 84, Folder 915)
    - Unidentified photographer, Benjamin Brooks, circa 1860 (Box 84, Folder 916)
    - Unidentified photographer, Martha Long and seven other women, 1899 (Box 84, Folder 917)
    - Unidentified photographer, Pair of portraits depicting a woman and man, probably wife and husband (Box 84, Folder 918)
    - Unidentified photographer, Portrait of a girl with short, curly hair (Box 84, Folder 919)
    - Unidentified photographer, Portrait of a man with a neck tie (Box 84, Folder 920)
    - Unidentified photographer, Portrait of a man with a hat and stockings (Box 84, Folder 921)
    - Unidentified photographer, Portrait of a man posed sitting and holding a hat (Box 84, Folder 922)
    - Unidentified photographer, Portrait of Mrs. Hopkins (Box 84, Folder 923)
    - Unidentified photographer, Portrait of a woman (Baker?) (Box 84, Folder 924)
    - Unidentified photographer, Portrait of a young girl (Box 84, Folder 925)
    - Unidentified photographer, Portrait of Sarah Hoton Priest, circa 1860 (Box 84, Folder 926)
  - Photographs on Glass
    This subseries includes examples of photographic positives applied or affixed to glass.
    Organized under two headings: Opaltypes and Photographic Prints on Glass
    - Opalotypes
      Opalotypes are photographic positives printed on or transferred to opal glass, also called milk glass, a white translucent glass made by the addition of oxides to basic silica soda glass
      - Rectangular opaltype with a portrait of an infant by Elite Photographic Studio, San Francisco, California, circa 1900 (Box 85, Folder 927)
      - Rectangular opaltype with a portrait of a man, circa 1900 (Box 85, Folder 928)
    - Photographic Prints on Glass
      This component consists of paper photographic prints affixed to glass.
      - Studio portrait of a man, made by W. H. Gregory, Brooklyn, New York, circa 1890 (Box 86, Folder 929)
      - Examples of photographic prints on glass by unidentified photographers, circa 1880-1910 (Box 86, Folder 930-937)
      - Memorial photograph with hand coloring of Agnes Gleaves (1895-1918) on glass (Box 87, Folder 938)
  - Miniature Photographs and Stanhopes
    This subseries includes photographs on a small scale.
    Organized under three headings: Miniature Photographs, Stamp Photographs and Microphotographs
    - Miniature Photographs
      Arranged alphabetically by photographer or manufacturer followed by examples by unidentified creators, arranged chronologically.
      - Detroit Novelty Studio, Detroit, Michigan, circa 1900 (Box 88, Folder 939)
      - Fawcett, E. E., Winona, Minnesota, circa 1892 (Box 88, Folder 940)
      - Hellis & Sons, London, England, circa 1900 (Box 88, Folder 941)
      - Hyde, N. H., Manchester, Iowa, circa 1885 (Box 88, Folder 942)
      - J. E. Tilton & Co., Boston, Massachusetts, circa 1870 (Box 88, Folder 943)
        Album with miniature copy photographs of studio portraits of United States Army generals and artworks
      - Jeanes, E. D., Allentown, Pennsylvania, circa 1885 (Box 88, Folder 944)
      - Lane Bros., Great Barrington and Housatonic, Massachusetts, 1894 (Box 88, Folder 945)
      - Lochman, Benjamin, Allentown, Pennsylvania, circa 1885 (Box 88, Folder 946)
      - Major, Darker, & Loraine, Barnstaple, England, circa 1905 (Box 88, Folder 947)
      - Mitchell, New York City, circa 1905 (Box 88, Folder 948)
        An advertising envelope for ping pong photos, a form of miniature photographs
      - Morse, S. G., Exeter, New Hampshire, circa 1890 (Box 88, Folder 949)
      - Novelty Photo Company, Peoria, Illinois, circa 1900 (Box 88, Folder 950)
      - O. K. Photo, circa 1900-1910 (Box 88, Folder 951)
      - Phillips, H. G., Williamsport, Pennsylvania, circa 1900 (Box 88, Folder 952)
      - Rosevear, Charles L., Toronto, Ontario, circa 1894-1903 (Box 88, Folder 953)
      - Stanton Photo Novelty, Springfield, Ohio, circa 1905-1910 (Box 88, Folder 954)
      - Stocking, George M., traveling photographer, circa 1900 (Box 88, Folder 955)
      - Walsh, Frank J., Trenton, New Jersey, circa 1890 (Box 88, Folder 956)
      - White, James A., Wautoma, Wisconsin, circa 1900 (Box 88, Folder 957)
      - Unidentified creators
        - Advertising card for the farewell tour of Mary France Scott Siddons, circa 1892 (Box 88, Folder 958)
        - Visiting cards with affixed miniature photographs, circa 1885-circa 1910 (Box 88, Folder 959-963)
        - Examples of miniature photographs, circa 1885-circa 1910 (Box 88, Folder 964-988)
        - Examples of multiple miniature photographs in presentation mats, circa 1890-1895 (Box 89, Folder 989-990)
    - Stamp Photographs
      Arranged alphabetically by creator.
      Photograph stamps, also known as photostamps, are photographs in the physical form of postage stamps.
      - Alsam Photostamp Co., New York City, business card with a stamp photograph portrait of Ruth Chatterton, circa 1935 (Box 90, Folder 991)
      - Bunn Studio, Syracuse, New York, Advertising envelope for stamp photographs, 1906 (Box 90, Folder 992)
      - Genelli Photographic Studio, St. Louis, Missouri, Examples of stamp photographs, circa 1900 (Box 90, Folder 993)
      - Pacific Stationers, Photograph stamps of the Golden Gate International Exposition, San Francisco, California, 1939-1940 (Box 90, Folder 994)
      - Unidentified photographer, Photograph stamps of Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, circa 1935-circa 1940 (Box 90, Folder 995)
      - Unidentified photographer, Photograph stamps with a portrait of a man identified as Pierce, circa 1935-circa 1940 (Box 90, Folder 996)
    - Stanhopes
      Stanhopes, also known as stanho-scopes, which represent microphotographs mounted under a magnifying glass. Photographers and manufacturers often inserted stanhopes in jewelry, writing equipment, or sewing accessories for decorative purposes.
      - Stanhope letter opener with an image of the marine pier and parade at Bognor Regis, England, circa 1880-circa 1900 (Box 91, Folder 997)
      - Stanhope measuring tape made in France with photographs of Wadebridge, England, created by McKee of Dublin, Ireland (Box 91, Folder 998)
  - Photographic Transparencies
    This subseries includes photographic transparencies, which represent photographs on transparent media designed for viewing by transmitted light.
    Organized under two headings: Autochromes and Transparencies
    - Autochromes
      Autochromes are color photographic transparencies on glass consisting of a photographic emulsion applied over a multicolored screen of minute starch grains dyed red, green, and blue-violet. This component also includes devices used for viewing autochromes.
      - Unidentified photographer, View of thistle flowers, circa 1910 (Box 92, Folder 999)
      - Unidentified photographer, Views of the Panama–Pacific International Exposition, San Francisco, California
        - Fountain of Energy, 1915 (Box 92, Folder 1000)
        - Palace of Fine Arts, 1915 (Box 92, Folder 1001)
      - Boyé, Otto H., San Francisco, California, Exterior portrait, in a viewer, of an elderly woman, circa 1915-circa 1920 (Box 93, Folder 1002)
      - Unidentified photographer, Exterior portrait, in a No. 4 1/2 Diascope manufactured by Lucian A. Dubernet, of a girl, circa 1915-circa 1920 (Box 94, Folder 1003)
    - Photographic Transparencies
      - D. Appleton and Company, View of the Lick Observatory, Mount Hamilton, California; a gelatin silver transparency on glass in a wooden frame, circa 1900 (Box 95)
      - Unidentified photographer, Studio portrait of a woman, bust figure vignette; a gelatin silver transparency on glass in a metal frame (Box 96)
      - Unidentified photographer, Two men and two boys posed standing in a hay wagon pulled by two horses, a toned gelatin silver transparency on glass printed by Gallo and housed in a wooden frame (Box 97(Oversize))
  - Photographic and Crayon Enlargements
    This subseries includes photographic and crayon enlargements, which represent copies of images or objects on a larger scale.
    Organized under three headings: Convex Photographic Enlargements, Flat Photographic Enlargements, and Crayon Enlargements
    - Convex Photographic Enlargements
      Convex photographic enlargements in this component are photographic prints physically shaped by the photographer into a convex lens shape.
      - Photographic enlargement oval-shaped of a composite photograph of a man with a drawing of a woman, circa 1890-circa 1900 (Box 98 (Oversize))
      - Photographic enlargement oval-shaped with hand coloring of a funeral flower decoration with "WC No. 59" expressed in flowers, as well as a photographic print that depicts a studio portrait of a woman, circa 1910 (Box 99 (Oversize))
        The decoration refers to Washington Camp, No. 59, Patriotic Order Sons of America, of Mapleton Depot, Pennsylvania
    - Flat Photographic Enlargements
      - Studio portrait of a boy, four women, and two men, circa 1900 (Box 100 (Oversize), Folder 1004)
      - Exterior portrait with hand coloring of two girls, a boy, woman, and man by a wooden fence, circa 1900-circa 1910 (Box 100 (Oversize), Folder 1005)
      - Johnson, Albert, Composite Photographs of Infants, 1922 (Box 101 (Broadside))
        2 photographic prints
    - Crayon Enlargements
      Arranged with an example of a sales kit followed by crayon enlargements organized under two headings: Convex Crayon Enlargements and Flat Crayon Enlargements
      Crayon enlargements are photographic portraits finished with liberal airbrushing and colored with pastels.
      - Sales kit with three crayon enlargements that individually depict a man, a woman, and a girl, circa 1890-1900 (Box 102 (Oversize))
        The enlargements are backed with canvas and attached to a wooden dowel with a cloth cover for carrying
      - Convex Crayon Enlargements
        Convex crayon enlargements in this component are crayon enlargements physically shaped by the photographer into a convex lens shape.
        - Crayon enlargement oval-shaped with hand coloring of a studio portrait man wearing a military uniform with a drawn border comprised of an eagle with a star, a United States flag, and a star-spangled shield, circa 1900 (Box 103 (Oversize))
        - Crayon enlargement oval-shaped with hand coloring of an exterior portrait of a man wearing a baseball uniform for "Chas. Green's Stars" and posed in the yard of a house, circa 1910 (Box 104 (Oversize))
        - Crayon enlargement oval-shaped with hand coloring of an exterior portrait of a young woman posed standing near a house, circa 1910 (Box 105 (Oversize))
        - Crayon enlargement oval-shaped with hand coloring of an exterior portrait of a young woman, circa 1910 (Box 106 (Oversize))
        - Crayon enlargement rectangle-shaped with hand coloring of a studio portrait of a woman and man, circa 1910-circa 1915 (Box 107 (Oversize))
        - Crayon enlargement oval-shaped with hand coloring of a studio portrait of two boys, circa 1915 (Box 108 (Oversize))
      - Flat Crayon Enlargements
        - Crayon enlargement with an ink stamp "T. J. O'Brien" with hand coloring of a studio portrait of an elderly woman; accompanied by a gilt oval mat, circa 1890 (Box 109 (Oversize), Folder 1006)
          Probably created by Thomas J. O'Brien, manager of The Pacific Portrait Co. in San Francisco, California
        - Two crayon enlargements oval-shaped with hand coloring that depict portraits of a woman and a man, circa 1895 (Box 109 (Oversize), Folder 1007)
        - Crayon enlargement of a portrait of a woman, identified in ink on the verso as Sarah Wise Martz, circa 1895 (Box 109 (Oversize), Folder 1008)
        - Crayon enlargement of a portrait of an infant, identified in pencil on the verso as Frank Edward Hansen, circa 1895 (Box 109 (Oversize), Folder 1009)
        - Crayon enlargement of a portrait of an infant, identified in pencil on the verso as Hans J. Hansen, circa 1895 (Box 109 (Oversize), Folder 1010)
        - Crayon enlargement with hand coloring of a studio portrait of a woman, identified in pencil on the verso as the sister of Hans Jørgen Hansen and aunt of Frank Hansen, circa 1895 (Box 109 (Oversize), Folder 1011)